你认为你了解历史 其实你了解的只是历史的结局
You think you know a story but you only know how it ends.
想要了解历史的真谛 就必须回到历史的开始
To get to the heart of the story you have to go back to the beginning.
大人
Your Grace.
坎贝吉奥主教大人来了
His Eminence, Cardinal Campeggio.
劳伦佐 我的老朋友
Lorenzo, my old friend.
亲爱的沃尔西
My dear Wolsey.
来
Come.
你得原谅我行动不便
Your Grace must forgive my incapacity.
上帝让我患上痛风 这是对我的一个考验
God has given me gout as a great trial.
现在… 王国陛下非常希望
Now, His Majesty is very keen…
特使会议能立即召开
…that the legatine court be set up straight away…
尽早裁定他离婚一事
…to determine the case for his annulment.
的确的确
Indeed, indeed.
我这里有教皇大人关于此事的手谕
I have the pope's written commission to decide upon this matter.
而且据我所知 这是不可更改的
And from my decision, there can be no appeal.
但现在…
And yet…
大人能不能让我喝点水
If Your Grace has some water.
倒水
Water.
可以的话 掺点酒
Mixed perhaps with a little wine.
但现在怎么样呢
And yet?
你我交情不浅了
You and I are old friends.
你我都是过来人了 沃尔西主教
And we are both men of the world, Cardinal Wolsey.
我还有个儿子和我一起
I even have a son who travels with me.
那又怎么样呢
And so?
教皇想要满足国王的请求 尽管有些困难
His Holiness wishes to satisfy the king, however difficult that might be.
撇开这些不说
But for all our sakes, would it not be better…
如果我们能劝国王放弃离婚 岂不是更好
…if you and I were to try and persuade His Majesty to give up his divorce?
当然 他对这个… 姑娘的热情会随着时间退却
Surely his passion for this girl will alter and fade with time…
热情终究是会减退的
…as all such passions inevitably do.
恐怕主教大人你有所不知
I fear Your Eminence may have proceeded here in ignorance.
那让我直说了吧
Let me make certain things plain to you.
如果不批准国王的离婚
If you do not grant the king his divorce…
教皇在英格兰的权威将不保
…papal authority in England will be annihilated.
你应该知道 现在德国的大部分地区
You should remember, the greater part of Germany…
都已经脱离了罗马教廷
…has already become estranged from Rome.
这里难保不发生同样的事
The same thing could happen here.
这将意味着王国的灭亡
It would mean the total ruin of the kingdom.
如果宣布你们的婚姻无效 会不会带来不良的后果
Is there any danger that they could declare your marriage valid?
沃尔西向我保证教皇会考虑我的利益
Wolsey has assured me that the pope has already decided in my favour.
会议只是形式
The trial's just for the sake of appearances…
安抚一下皇帝而已
…a way of appeasing the emperor.
那我们可以开始策划婚礼了吗
Then we can start planning the wedding?
是的
Yes.
是的 吾爱
Yes, my love.
谨慎起见 还需要下点别的工夫
Also for the sake of appearances, there is something else.
我要继续和凯瑟林一起用餐
For a while, I shall have to share Catherine's table.
偶尔还得和她共寝
And sometimes her bed.
- 共寝？- 这没什么
- Her bed? - It's nothing.
我的律师建议我这样做 否则会落下把柄
My lawyers have just advised me that to do otherwise might risk countersuit.
会侵犯了她与丈夫同居的权力
I could be seen to be acting against her conjugal rights.
你觉得回去和你妻子共寝不算什么 ？
You think it's nothing to go back to bed with your wife?
你觉得会发生什么吗
What do you think is going to happen?
就像以前发生过的那样
What usually happens.
你对我就这么点信任
How little you trust me.
我信任你
I trust you.
我爱你
I love you.
这事不该责怪凯瑟林 也不怪我
Catherine is not to blame for this. Nor am I.
事实是 大人 我们违背了上帝的法律
But the fact is, Excellence, we broke God's law…
此罪难赦
…for which there can be no dispensation.
你应该知道这让我的良知倍受煎熬
You understand how deeply this touches my conscience…
我到底还有多久才能解脱
…and how quickly I need it to be resolved.
我非常同情
I do. I sympathise.
教皇陛下也是
As does His Holiness, naturally.
同时教皇陛下也给您提供了
But His Holiness also suggests to Your Majesty…
另一个选择
…another possible solution.
我已经对主教大人说得很清楚了 陛下…
I have already made it plain to Your Eminence that His Majesty…
不 不 不 普里哥 这可不一样 朋友
No, this is not the same, my friend.
这个办法 国王陛下应该会满意
This is a solution which should very much please His Majesty.
说来听听
What is it?
教皇了解王后陛下是个虔诚的人
His Holiness is aware of the queen's great piety.
她本人也提及过 她对圣母圣徒等的敬爱
She herself has spoken of it, her love for the Mother of God, for the saints.
教皇认为可以规劝王后
And he wonders if Her Majesty might be persuaded…
像路易十二曾经的妻子 珍妮－德－瓦洛瓦一样
…like Jeanne de Valois, the sometime wife of Louis Xll…
宣布放弃婚姻
…to abdicate her marriage…
遁入空门
…and retreat to a nunnery.
你觉得如何 沃尔西
What do you think, Wolsey?
这当然能把事情简单化
Well, it would certainly expedite matters.
免去了审议的麻烦
It would save us the pain of a trial.
鉴于是自愿行为
And since it would be voluntary…
也就不会激怒她的侄子 皇帝陛下
…it couldn't offend her nephew, the emperor.
此外 这也能让王后体面的退位
And moreover, it would afford Her Majesty an honourable retirement.
你马上去和王后商量
You will put this to her right away.
是的 陛下
Majesty.
王后陛下能不能考虑一下这个提议
Will Your Majesty at least consider the proposal?
等我和我的丈夫 国王陛下谈话以后
I will give you my answer in due course…
我会及时给你答复的
…after I have spoken with the king, my husband.
神父 一会能听我忏悔吗
Father, will you hear my confession later?
好的 孩子
Yes, my child.
- 王后陛下 - 主教大人
- Your Majesty. - Your Eminence.
王后陛下
Your Majesty.
我请求您满足国王的要求
I beg that you yield to the king's will.
- 他的什么要求 - 如主教大人所说
- And what is his will? - As His Eminence proposes.
选择加入一个宗教组织
That you join a religious community of your choosing…
发誓永守贞洁
…and take a vow of perpetual chastity.
你还有脸和我提贞洁
You speak to me of chastity?
忘记你的情妇和两个孩子了吗 主教大人
Have you not a mistress and two children, Your Eminence?
陛下已是而立之年了
Your Majesty is entering the third period of your natural life.
您已经为这个世界树立了一个良好的榜样
You spent the first two setting a good example.
这样一来更能为您的美德锦上添花
With this single act, you could put the seal on all your good actions.
请起来 大人
Please rise, Your Grace.
无论是什么理由
It is not seemly for a man of your dignity…
你这样尊贵的人都不该在公共场合有失身份
…to be seen to beg in public, whatever the cause.
主教大人
Eminence.
- 你和坎贝吉奥谈过了？- 是的
- So you talked to Campeggio? - Yes.
我告诉他 要经过你的允许 我才能做出决定
I told him I could not give an answer without Your Majesty's permission.
那要怎么答复他
And what answer will you give him?
- 我会告诉他事实 - 凯瑟林
- I will tell him the truth. - Catherine.
现在全世界都知道 你我的婚姻是不正当的
All the world now agrees that your marriage to me was unjust.
你本人也必须承认
Even you must acknowledge it.
要么你自愿 要么我逼你
So unless you agree to take the veil, I shall have to force you.
你允许我和坎贝吉奥谈话了吗
Do I have your permission to talk to Campeggio?
如果你不允许 我不会对他说什么
I will not speak to him if you do not want me to.
- 我的夫人 - 安妮夫人
- My lady. - Lady Anne.
克伦威尔大人
Master Cromwell.
你… 你有国王那边的消息吗
Do you have a message from the king?
我们都应该记得
I think we understand each other.
我们彼此的朋友 费西先生
A mutual friend, a Mr. Fish, now living in exile in Holland…
现在被放逐到荷兰 他有礼物带给你
…has sent me a gift for you.
什么礼物 克伦威尔先生
What is it, Master Cromwell?
「顺从基督」 威廉－廷代尔写的
The Obedience of the Christian Man by William Tyndale.
里面指责了教皇
It contains many good criticisms of the papacy…
还有教士的无知和贪婪
…and of the arrogance and abuses of priests.
你会觉得很有启发
You will find it most illuminating.
你千万不能让别人看见
But always and ever be cautious as to whom you show this.
要知道拥有这种书就算是异教
You must know it might be accounted heresy even to possess it.
而沃尔西对于绞杀异教徒乐此不疲…
And Wolsey is still keen enough to prosecute heretics…
就这样称呼我们 我们这些信仰正教的人
…as we are called, who embrace the true religion.
我会的
I will.
上帝保佑你 克伦威尔先生
And God bless you, Master Cromwell.
等等
Wait.
能不能把这个转交给国王…
Please, will you give this to the king?
带着我的爱
With my love.
是的 夫人
My lady.
过来
Come here.
鸡…
Chicken.
Chick…
这才乖
Good chicken.
嘘… 嘘…
shh… shh…
别乱跑
Don't run away.
抓到你了
Got you.
你从来没告诉过我你的名字
You never even told me your name.
- 简 - 简
- Jane. - Jane.
为什么离开宫廷
Why did you leave the court?
你姐姐去世以后…
When your sister died…
我姐姐还在这儿 托马斯－塔里斯
My sister is still here, Thomas Tallis.
她没有离开我
She hasn't left me.
她不会离开我
She can't leave me.
你也能看见她 不是吗
You can see her too, can't you?
我从伦敦一路过来
I came all the way from London.
我真的希望你能回到宫廷
And I really want you to come back to court.
为什么
Why?
你喜欢我姐姐胜过我 我看得出
You liked my sister more than me. I could tell.
我想娶你 珍
I want to marry you, Jane.
[拉丁文]在父亲 孩子 还有圣明之下 阿门
Pater filius et Spiritus Sanctus.
你想忏悔什么
What is it you wish to confess?
神父 我想告诉你 我和陛下的兄长
Father, I wish to tell you about my first marriage to Prince Arthur…
亚瑟王子第一次的婚姻
…His Majesty's older brother.
我听说过 你继续
I know of it. Go on.
他根本就不认识我
He never knew me.
我可以用最神圣的东西起誓
I swear to you, under the sacramental oath…
我和亨利结婚之前 我并没有和亚瑟有过婚姻之实
…I was intacta e incorrupta da lui comme venne dal ventre di sua madra.
我想搞清楚
I want to be clear.
你说你从出生到现在
You say you were untouched and unviolated by Prince Arthur…
就从来没有和亚瑟王子有过任何肉体接触
…as when you came from the womb of your mother?
是的 神父
Yes, Father.
你和陛下结婚的时候还是处女
So you came to the king's bed a virgin, intacta e incorrupta?
是的 神父
Yes, Father.
神父 我并无意冒犯
Father, I say in all humility…
但我不能接受你的提议
…I cannot accede to your request.
我是亨利合法的妻子
I am the true and legitimate wife of His Majesty.
你的建议我不能采纳
Therefore your proposal is inadmissible.
无论前途
Come what may…
我与我的婚姻共存亡
…I will live and die in that vocation to matrimony…
这是上帝的旨意
…to which God has called me.
我明白了
I understand.
还有 我允许你违反忏悔的沉默约定
Furthermore, I give you permission to break the seal of the confessional…
把我说的话告诉全世界
…and tell the whole world what I have told you.
亨利要你回宫廷
Henry wants you back at court.
你毕竟是他的姐姐
You are his sister after all.
他带着那个荡妇招摇过市 我怎么能回去
How can I return while he flaunts himself with his slut?
这就等于我默许了他的举动
I would be seen to be approving of his ridiculous liaison.
玛格丽特 没有国王的照应 我们两人将一无所有
Margaret, you and I must stay in the king's good graces or we are nothing.
他爱娶谁就娶谁
Let him marry who he wishes.
这就是你的哲学 不是吗 查尔斯
That was always your philosophy, wasn't it, Charles?
真是讽刺
So very cynical.
所以你才和那个罪恶的博林交好
Is that why you keep company with that devil Boleyn?
他帮我们重回宫廷那阵 你不是也很喜欢他吗
You liked him enough once when he helped us back to court.
现在表现得那么愤世嫉俗
Or were you just being cynical?
我当时不知道他的算盘 现在我知道了 我鄙视他
I didn't see all of his game. Now I do, I despise him.
我也是 但我更恨沃尔西
So do I. But I hate Wolsey more.
- 这样的婚姻只是权宜之计 - 就像我们
- It's a marriage of expedience. - Rather like ours?
不 我爱你
No. I loved you.
你懂爱字的含意吗 查尔斯
You don't know the meaning of the word.
你可以爱
You can love…
一年 一个月 一天…
…perhaps for a year or a month, a day…
甚至一个小时
…even for an hour.
在那一小时里
And in that hour…
你爱得那么深…
…I do believe you love as well and deeply…
和任何男人一样
…as any man.
但那一小时过后 你就不爱了
But after that hour, you love not.
你就去爱另一个
You love another…
再另一个
…and then another.
你的爱…
Your love…
很慷慨 也很伤人
…is most generous where it is most hurtful.
- 玛格丽特 - 别装傻 查尔斯
- Margaret. - Don't play the fool.
这可不像你
Doesn't become you.
主教大人
Eminence.
我要见坎贝吉奥主教大人
I need to see Cardinal Campeggio.
很抱歉 大人不舒服
Forgive me. My father is indisposed.
况且 对于现在的情况他已经无能为力
In any case, there is nothing further he can do for the time being.
他送了些报告回罗马
He has sent some reports to Rome…
必须等待教皇陛下的指示
…and must await the replies from His Holiness.
在此期间
And in the meantime…
可怜的父亲需要休息 恢复体力
…my poor father needs to rest and restore his strength.
- 安妮夫人 - 晚上好 安妮夫人
- Lady Anne. - Good evening, Lady Anne Boleyn.
- 这就是那位叫博林的情妇吗 - 是的 就是她
- There is the Mistress Boleyn? - Yes, there she is.
国王为了这个女人要牺牲他的婚姻
The girl for whom the king…
牺牲一个仁慈 充满爱心的王后
…would sacrifice his marriage to a most gracious and loving queen.
我尽力劝过他
I have tried to argue him out of his course.
但我打赌 就算是天使下凡也劝不了他
But I swear that an angel descending from heaven would not dissuade him.
你觉得他们是否已经联合在一起了？
Do you think they have taken things to the ultimate conjunction?
我收到了萨福克 诺福克公爵 和博林爵爷的联合请愿书
I've received a petition from the dukes of Suffolk, Norfolk and Lord Boleyn…
说离婚一事 受到大部分国民的支持
…saying the divorce has the support of the people of England.
只要主教大人出去看看民众
As Your Eminence would quickly discover…
很快就能发现
…if you stepped outside these doors and saw the people…
那是弥天大谎
…that is a manifest lie.
正好相反 人们爱戴他们的王后
On the contrary, the people love their queen.
他们这样做有充分的理由
And they have every reason to do so.
失陪一下
If you'll excuse me.
- 沃尔西 - 王后陛下拒绝了提议
- Wolsey. - Her Majesty has refused the offer.
你很惊奇吗
Are you surprised?
而且 坎贝吉奥告诉我
However, Campeggio tells me…
教皇愿意承认 您和博林情妇
…that the pope is prepared to consider legitimising any children…
生下的孩子是合法的
…that you might have with Mistress Boleyn…
无论你们是否结婚
…whether you are married or not.
你生气吗
Are you mad?
你应该取得比这更好的结果
You're gonna have to do a lot better than that.
打扰一下 门多萨大使
Forgive me, Ambassador Mendoza.
我初来乍到
I am new to this court.
那些和国王交谈的人都是谁
Who are these men talking with the king?
理齐福德爵爷 是安妮－博林的父亲 诺福克是她的叔叔
Lord Rochford is the father of Anne Boleyn, Norfolk is her uncle.
和萨福克公爵一样 都是沃尔西的死敌
Like the Duke of Suffolk, they are Wolsey's sworn enemies…
宫里的人都知道
…and everyone at court knows it.
为了拉他下水 他们会不择手段
They would stop at nothing to bring him down.
国王还是信任他吗
Yet the king still loves him?
不如以前了
Not so much as before, perhaps.
但绝对不能低估了主教大人
But the cardinal should never be underestimated.
能告诉我你对这事的看法吗
May I know what you think of the king's matter?
皇帝的态度不是秘密
It is no secret that the emperor is outraged…
他很愤怒国王对王后的行为
…at the king's behaviour toward the queen.
我告诉你 你可千万不能说出去 他写过信给教皇陛下
And I can tell you in strict confidence that he has written to His Holiness…
要求在罗马 而不是在这里 解决这个问题
…demanding that the matter be settled in Rome, not here.
他有没有想过 以别的办法干涉
He would not seek to interfere in any other way?
什么别的办法
In what way?
如果王后被废
Well, if the queen were to be renounced…
他有没有考虑以她的名义武力干预
…might he consider military intervention on her behalf?
他没这么说过
He has not said so.
- 有人问过他吗 - 没有
- Has anyone asked him? - No.
目前还没有
Not yet.
- 陛下 - 玛格丽特…
- Your Majesty. - Margaret.
别和她在一起 她不值得
Not her. She's not worth it.
她只是个贱货
She's a cheap nothing.
睁开眼睛 好好看看她
Open your eyes. Look at her.
看看你自己
Look at yourself.
管好你自己的婚姻
Look to your own marriage.
你还好吗
How are you?
在燃烧
Burning.
欲火焚身
Burning with impatience.
夫人 沃翰大主教
My lady, Archbishop Warham…
和唐斯多主教求见
…and Bishop Tunstall are here to see you.
大人们
My lords.
我知道你们是特使会议的成员
I understand that you are among my council for the legatine court.
作为正直的人 你们的职责是对得起上帝和良心
As honourable men whose first duty is to God and your conscience…
我欢迎你们
…you are welcome.
- 是国王派你们来的吗 - 是的 陛下
- Has the king sent you? - Yes, Your Majesty.
那我们来讨论一下案子吧
We must discuss your brief.
我全心全意爱着国王陛下
I have nothing against His Majesty, whom I love with all my being…
只是恨他的顾问
…only against his advisers…
还有那个有野心毁了这个国家的女人
…and a certain woman whose ambition would ruin a kingdom.
夫人 我们不是来讨论案子的
Madam, we are not here to discuss a brief or any such.
- 但是… - 我们是来汇报的
- But… - We came here to report, madam…
谣传境外有人密谋刺杀国王
…that rumours of plots against the life of His Majesty are abroad.
还有坎贝吉奥大主教
And plots against Cardinal Campeggio.
如果密谋成功
If any such plots were to be successful…
显然您和您的女儿
…then clearly both you and your daughter…
都脱不了嫌疑
…would be suspected of involvement.
我简直不敢相信国王会听信这些谣言
I cannot believe the king would give credence to such rumours…
他应该知道 你们也应该知道
…since he knows, as you know…
我珍惜我丈夫的生命胜过我自己的
…that I value my husband's life even much more than my own.
夫人 还有一个情况
Madam, there is yet another complaint.
你太轻率 在民众面前露面太多
That you are flippant and show yourself too much to the people.
您喜欢他们的欢呼 并对他点头微笑挥手
That you rejoice in their acclaim, smiling, nodding and waving at them.
有此可见 你恨国王
Therefore, we suppose that you hate the king.
凭什么这么说
Why should you suppose that?
夫人 因为你不肯承认 和他的婚姻生活是一种罪恶
Because you don't accept that all this time you've been living in sin with him.
即使现在真相大白 你也拒绝国王的慷慨提议
Even when the truth has been revealed, you refuse to accept the king's offer…
去侍奉上帝
…offer to retire to a religious house.
又来了
That again.
我已经答复过了 上帝并没有招呼我去做修女
I have answered for that already. God never called me to a nunnery.
我是国王陛下合法的真正的妻子
I am His Majesty's true and legitimate wife.
- 夫人 看在上帝的份儿上… - 是的 看在上帝的份儿上
- Madam, for the love of God… - Yes, for the love of God.
你自己也公认过 主教大人
As you yourself once professed, archbishop.
你告诉人们我的罪名是莫须有的
You told people that you knew my case to be true.
现在为什么改变主意
So, what changed your mind?
嗯
Emm.
是因为沃尔西吗
Was it Wolsey?
告诉我 你是不是对你在人间的地位
Tell me, do you prefer your place in this earth…
比对在天堂的地位更看重
…rather than your place in heaven?
- 对这些指责你还没有答复 - 先生
- You have not answered the charges. - Sir.
我被自己的律师起诉 这让我无法接受
I consider it hard indeed to be charged and accused by my own lawyers.
这算什么公正
Where is the justice in that?
我不会再见你们 你们也不再代表我
I will speak to you no more, but you will not act for me.
凯瑟林
Catherine.
你为什么否认我的公正
Why do you go on denying me justice?
你真是无情
You're so heartless.
充满了恨意
So full of hatred.
我不要再骗自己说你爱我了
I can't persuade myself any longer that you love me.
我的确爱你
I do love you.
我从未停止过爱你 你知道
I have never ceased to love you. You know that.
我不知道
I don't know it.
也许你该离我们的女儿远点…
Perhaps you should be kept away from our daughter…
免得给她坏的影响 让她恨我
…in case you start poisoning her mind against me.
你怎么能对我说这样的话
How can you say these things to me?
我们一起走过那么久 曾经在彼此心里有过那样的分量
After all this time, after all that we have meant to each other.
我希望你能讲道理
I'm only asking you to be reasonable.
我讲道理 不肯讲道理的人是你
I am being reasonable. It is you who will not be reasonable.
你到底想要什么 托马斯
What is it you really want, Thomas?
- 想要什么 - 对于你的生活
- Want? - In life.
你想要什么
What do you want?
我不知道 我想是旅行吧
I don't know. Travel, I suppose.
如果可以的话 去冒险
Adventure, if I could.
旅行 你想去哪儿
Travel? Where would you go?
你没听书吗
Have you not heard?
航海家已经出发了
Sea discoverers to new worlds have gone.
卡伯特去新的大陆 有的去美洲和印度
Cabot to Newfoundland, others to America, the Indies.
还有的去中国 丝绸王国 马可－波罗故事中的国度
Some speak of China, Cathay, the fabled lands of Marco Polo.
你会去哪儿
But where would you go?
我会从这里出发…
I'd set out here…
头发是充满伏兵和圈套的丛林
…though the hair is a forest of ambush and snares.
但是眉毛能让人平静 像安宁的平原
But the brow becalms us when it's smooth and plain.
眼窝对于船队很危险
And the dark pools of the eyes are dangerous to our ship…
陷进去就会失事
…for to be drawn into them would be shipwreck.
鼻子就像子午线 带我们到嘴唇
The nose, like the first meridian, directs us down…
幸运之岛
…to the Islands Fortunate…
我就在这里
…the swelling lips.
抛锚
I would anchor here…
听海妖的歌声
…and hear the siren songs.
然后继续航行
Then sailing on…
越过下巴这个海角
…past the glorious promontory of chin.
我们也许会遇到一些海岛
We may encounter survivors…
然后航行到你的印度
…as we travel down towards your India.
在大西洋上停下
And we pause at the Atlantic navel.
海浪会带着我们
Then the current carries our pilot on…
去到另一个丛林
…to another forest…
会有很多船只遇难
…where many are shipwrecked…
旅行到此为止
…and no further ever get.
我有了个新的座右铭
I have a new motto.
是什么
What is it?
你得自己去找
You'll have to find it.
在哪儿
Where is it?
在一条丝带上 藏在某个地方
On a piece of ribbon hidden somewhere.
是不是… 这儿
Is it here?
不
No.
- 那这里呢 - 不
- Down there? - No.
那在这里吗
Is it down here?
我不能再等了
I can't wait much longer.
你不用再等了
You won't have to.
嗯…
Emm…
陛下… 事情又被拖延下了
Your Majesty, there are fresh delays.
大家都见不到坎贝吉奥
No one can see Campeggio.
快告诉我 在哪儿
Where is it? Tell me.
也许有人是故意的
What if someone is deliberately stalling?
有意拖延 寻找借口
Delaying things, making excuses.
坎贝吉奥
Campeggio?
不 是别的人 离你更近的人
No. No, someone else, someone much closer to you.
我摸到了
I'm touching it.
[法语]事情会
Ainsi sera…
[法语]朝着有利的方向发展
grogne qui grogne.
事情会朝着有利的方向发展
That's how it's going to be.
让他们抱怨去吧
Let them grumble.
一个和你更接近的人
Someone much closer to you.
关于坎贝吉奥 我想问问你的意见
I want to ask you frankly about Campeggio.
你相信他吗
Do you trust him?
你觉得他妥协了吗
Do you think he's compromised?
谁知道呢 也许他收了皇帝的贿赂
Who knows, perhaps he's getting a pension from the emperor.
据我所知 劳伦佐不是这样的人
As I know it, Lorenzo is the least prejudicial of men.
他本人也受够了查尔斯手下的人
And he has suffered personally at the hands of Charles's soldiers.
他们到达罗马的时候 洗劫了他家
When they entered Rome, they ransacked his house.
我觉得他对皇帝没什么好感
I don't believe he has love for the emperor.
那他为什么拖延会议
Then why is he delaying the trial?
他们有些技术上的东西需要解决 仅此而已
Well, there are some technical matters that need to be resolved, that's all.
陛下您根本不用担心
There is nothing for Your Majesty to be concerned about.
该死的 根本就不是坎贝吉奥 就是你
Goddamn it. It's not Campeggio at all, it's you.
就是你在拖 你对离婚的事漠不关心
You are the one delaying things. You've gone cold on this divorce.
你一开始就不信我
Perhaps you never believed in it.
你对我撒谎 假装站在我这边
You lied to me, pretending to be on my side.
陛下 我向您 向上帝 以我的名誉起誓
Majesty, I swear before you and before God on my honour…
我是您最谦卑的仆人
…I am your most humble servant.
在这个世界上 我最希望的事情就是您能离婚
And there is nothing on earth I covet so much as advancing your divorce.
让它实现是我的职责
And to bring it to pass is my continual study…
也是我最虔诚的愿望
…and my most ardent desire…
我愿意为此献出我的生命 我的肉体 我的鲜血
…for which I am ready to expend my life and my body and my blood…
上帝啊 请您帮助我
…so help me God.
来 大人 别这么沮丧
Come, Your Grace. Don't be so dismayed.
你应该理解我的不耐心
You understand my impatience.
我知道不是你
I know it's not you.
我相信你
I trust you.
我对你了解已久
I've known you a long time.
来 我们谈谈别的
Come, let's talk of other things.
莫尔大人
By God's body, Master More.
王子的愤怒意味着死亡
The anger of the prince means death.
陛下
Majesty.
克伦威尔先生 我要你去罗马
I want you to go to Rome, Mr. Cromwell.
我要你去让该死的教皇服从
I want you to force His fucking Holiness into submission.
如果有必要的话 告诉他 如果他不取消我该死的婚姻
If necessary, telling him that if he does not grant me my annulment…
英格兰将不再听从教廷差遣
…England will withdraw its submission to Rome…
我也不再效忠他
…and I will withdraw my allegiance to him.
让他知道 我可不是说说而已
And make sure he knows this is no idle threat.
如果他不能满足我 我说到做到
I mean it and I will do it if he does not satisfy me.
叫萨福克公爵进来
Send in the Duke of Suffolk.
公爵大人 国王召见
My Lord Duke, the king summons you.
查尔斯
Charles.
我有事要你办
I have a task for you.
我要你去巴黎见弗朗西斯国王
I want you to go to Paris and seek out King Francis.
细细问一下坎贝吉奥的底细
Question him closely about Campeggio.
问问他们之间有什么交情 他是什么样的人
Ask him what kind of dealings he's had with him, what kind of man he is.
是否诚实 有没有做教皇的野心
Is he honest? Does he have any ambitions to be pope?
他和皇帝私下有没有什么交情
And ask him, does he have any secret dealings with the emperor?
我马上出发
I'll leave at once.
还有 查尔斯
And, Charles…
跟他谈一谈关于沃尔西
…ask him about Wolsey.
要他直言不讳
I want to know everything he knows about him.
- 明白了吗 - 嗯
- You understand? - Emm.
我要知道沃尔西到底站在哪边
I want to know whose side Wolsey's on.
托马斯爵士
Sir Thomas.
最伟大的王后
Most gracious sovereign lady.
我带了费西主教来见你
I have brought Bishop Fisher to see you.
我相信他能给您最诚挚的建议
I believe he can offer you true and devoted counsel.
谢谢你 托马斯爵士
Thank you, Sir Thomas.
陛下
Majesty.
请
Please.
主教大人 你真的想代理我的案件吗？
Lord Bishop, are you certain that you wish to act for me?
你得知道 这很困难 也许会给你带来危险
You must be aware of the dangers and difficulties you may face.
如果你想置身事外 我也可以理解
I would understand if you would prefer peace and tranquillity.
夫人 没有公正和上帝之爱
Gentle madam, what peace or tranquillity can there be…
何谈自身的宁静
…without justice and the love of God?
我详细地看了对您的指控
I have studied the case against you very carefully.
他们会抓住一点
They will no doubt press the fact that the pope's dispensation…
就是教皇给您和国王的结婚许可
…to allow you to marry the king was technically faulty…
是有错误的 于是婚姻无效
…and therefore invalid.
要想克服 这些所谓的技术错误
But the obvious way of resolving any such technical deficiency…
不是宣布婚姻无效
…is not to declare the marriage null and void…
而是重新颁发合法的结婚证
…but to issue fresh and more perfect dispensation.
无论如何 持续那么长久的婚姻
In any case, the continuance of so long space…
自然也就合理合法
…has rendered the marriage honest.
而且以教会作主为原则
And the principle of supplet ecclesia…
「一切由教会作主」
…let the church provide.
在教皇颁发的许可证里也有诸多漏洞的
…has itself made good any defects in the pope's dispensation.
意思是我们可能赢
Then you suppose we may win?
我们可能赢得案子
We may win the argument, yes.
但我得假装这对我们不利
But I cannot pretend that it will avail us much.
我们要坚持住
We shall still try.
打起精神来 夫人
Be of good cheer, madam…
天使站在我们一边
…for we are on the side of the angels.
最大的牌是红心
Hearts are trumps.
怎么了
What is it?
我有克伦威尔的消息了
I've heard from Cromwell.
他终于得以晋见教皇 但信上写 他无能为力
He was eventually allowed access to the pope but wrote in desperation.
为什么
Why?
他觉得克莱门特不会帮我
He doesn't believe Clement will do anything for me.
他说… 「这也许是他的过错 但这违背了他的信条」
He said, " It might be in his paternoster, but it's nothing in his creed."
意思是 教皇愿意为我的灵魂祈祷
The pope might pray for me to solve my problems.
但是他不能承诺为我做任何事
But he won't personally commit to doing anything about it.
亮牌
Show.
给我看
Show me.
的确 在教皇特使路经法国时我们款待过他
We entertained the pope as he passed.
我本人也和坎贝吉奥交谈过
And I spoke personally to Campeggio.
他是个很谨慎的人
He was very careful.
虽然只说了几句话 但我看得出他有所保留
But even in the few words he spoke, I thought he dissembled.
哪些方面有所保留
In what way dissembled?
我觉得他表现出的只是一面 而隐藏了另一面
I think he shows one face but conceals another.
他被派去做这件事 但他私底下很蔑视
He has been asked to deal with a matter he secretly despises.
我对国王 我的兄长 有个建议
So my advice to the king, my brother…
就是不要太相信任何人
…is to not put too much trust in any man…
以免被人出卖
…in case he should be deceived.
你觉得沃尔西也是这样的人吗
And would you say the same of Cardinal Wolsey?
我并不反感主教大人
I have nothing against His Eminence.
那是当然
Of course not.
但你认为他对离婚会有什么看法呢
But what do you think his attitude is towards the divorce?
我个人认为 他倒是希望能离婚
As I could tell, he wanted the divorce to go through…
因为他本人对王后并没有什么感情
…because he has no love for the queen.
同时…
At the same time…
同时
At the same time?
我感觉他和教皇陛下很有默契
It is my impression that he has marvellous intelligence with the pope.
总是能理解对方 和坎贝吉奥大主教也是如此
They understand each other. And also with Cardinal Campeggio.
因此 国王应该意识到
Therefore, if he has such understanding with them…
他们不会对离婚的事有任何推进作用
…and they are not minded to advance the matter…
要我直说的话
…then, to speak frankly to you…
国王应该自己多关心一下了
…I think the king should take a closer interest in it himself.
这就是我的建议
That is my advice.
陛下
Majesty.
他去哪儿
Where is he going?
去陪他的新情妇了
I'm sure to service his latest mistress.
哪里有这个必要 他已经有一个这么美丽的妻子了
Now, why would he have to do that when he has such a beautiful wife?
这话你该去问他 先生
You should ask him, monsieur.
你不想报复他吗
Don't you ever want to pay him back?
当然 一直都想 但我是个女人
Of course, always. I'm a woman.
那么和我上床
Then go to bed with me.
只要你愿意
If you like.
但是请你先告诉我
But tell me first…
你的美丽妻子呢
…how is your beautiful wife?
- 她… - 她就和我一样 不是吗
- She's… - She is just like me, non?
对你的艳遇睁一只眼闭一只眼
You have affairs and she ignores it.
为了报复你而和别人做爱 为了什么
To make love for revenge or pain, what is that?
只会让人心力憔悴
It hurts the mind.
会缩小的 你明白吗 先生
And the soul, it shrinks.
你的灵魂会变渺小
The soul grows smaller.
也许会彻底死去
And perhaps it even dies.
- 大人 - 大人
- Your Grace. - Your Grace.
让我们单独谈谈
Leave us.
会议要开始了
The trial is coming.
的确 大人
Indeed, Your Grace.
我想再次提醒你
I want to make it plain to you again.
如果不批准离婚
If you refuse to grant the divorce…
你就是对教皇不满
…you will provoke a marvellous opinion against the pope…
对教廷 乃至对教会的不满
…against the papal courts, and against the papacy itself.
我只对圣父本人负责 负责公正地处理这件事
I am obliged to the Holy Father to seek truth and justice in this matter.
大人 我也打算这么做
And that, Your Grace, I will attempt to do…
上帝为我作证
…as God is my witness.
你好像还是不明白
You still do not seem to understand.
那让我再把话说明白点
So let me spell it out for you.
如果你作出对国王不利的判决
If you fail to find in favour of the king…
你会失去国王
…you will lose the king…
以及他为罗马奉献的疆土
…and the devotion of his realm to Rome.
你也会彻底毁了我
And you will also utterly destroy me.
这一点我绝不能容忍
And that I cannot allow.
我完全明白
I totally understand.
你要坚定信念 沃尔西主教
You must have faith, Cardinal Wolsey.
上帝会帮助我
God help me.
大人们 沃尔西很明显已经妥协了
My lords, it has become obvious that Wolsey is severely compromised…
他和国王那种亲密信任的关系已经不再了
…and no longer enjoys the affinity he used to share with His Majesty.
国王对他已经起了疑心
The king is suspicious of his first minister.
我们应该顺水推舟
And we should encourage those suspicions.
是时候把他拉下来了
It is time to bring him down.
就是这本小册子
Here is a pamphlet.
它嘲弄了他在职期间的傲慢 奢侈
You see, it mocks his period in office as a time of pride, waste…
镇压手段和他无用的政策
…repression and ineffectual policies.
是时候开始传播了
It's ready for distribution.
我们要马上要求逮捕沃尔西和他的幕僚
We shall call for the arrest of Wolsey and his agents…
截获他们的信件文书 彻底检查他在职期间的
…the impounding of their papers and a thorough examination…
任何行为
…of his administration.
他的腐败会暴露出来 叛国罪也逃不掉
His corruption will be exposed and treason guaranteed.
现在 博林 得由你的小女儿
All that remains, Boleyn, is for your daughter to prove to the king…
向国王证明 他的怀疑是正确的
…that all his suspicions are justified.
然后… 主教将无法翻身
And then the cardinal will be naked to his enemies.
- 敬英格兰 - 敬英格兰
- To England. - To England.
- 我的主啊 - 对不起 对不起
- Christ. - Sorry, sir. Sorry.
- 对不起 - 狗杂种
- I'm sorry. - Stupid dog!
[拉丁文]以圣父 圣子和圣灵的名义
In nomine patris filius et Spiritus Sancto.
- 阿门 - 阿门
- Amen. - Amen.
我宣布 此次会议
I declare this legatine court…
由克莱门特教皇陛下授权的会议 现在开始
…commissioned by His Holiness, Pope Clement, is now in session.
在这里说的每一句话必须宣誓
And all that is said here is said under oath…
并受到万能上帝的监督
…and in the presence of God Almighty.
请国王陛下首先就此案进行陈述
I call upon His Majesty to speak first as to this matter.
主教大人知道我今天站到这里的原因
Your Eminences know well what cause I have to be here.
涉及到关于我婚姻的一些事实
It concerns some scruples I have regarding my marriage…
这刺痛了我的良知
…which prick my conscience.
我广泛征求意见以解开真相
I have consulted widely to discover the truth.
我在《利末记》看到 这是违法上帝的法律的
And I have read in Leviticus that it was against God's law…
娶自己兄长的妻子是一桩罪过
…and a sin, for me to marry my brother's wife.
主教大人
Your Eminences…
我不是唯一怀疑自己婚姻合法性的人
…I am not the only one who questions the validity of my marriage.
我的主教们和我一样深怀疑虑
All of my bishops share my doubts…
他们起草了一个情愿书希望澄清此事
…and they have signed a petition to put the matter to question.
大人 我可以说
My Lords, I tell you now…
我从未在此类文件上签过字
…I never signed my name to any such document.
- 如果签了 那是… - 没有要求你发言…
- And if it appears there… - Court has not invited you to speak.
如果唐斯托主教未经我同意
If it appears there, then Bishop Tunstall wrote it…
代我签署
…without my consent.
现在由国王陛下陈述 先生
The king has the floor. Sit down, sir.
- 坐好 - 我现在不和你辩
- Sit. - I'm not going to argue with you now.
毕竟这只是你一个人的看法
After all, you are but one man.
就这件事
As for the main issue…
如果有人问起 为什么我等了那么久才提起
…if I am asked why I waited so long to bring this question to trial…
我据实回答
…I shall answer truthfully.
是因为我对王后陛下无比的爱
That it was the great love that I bore for Her Majesty…
这爱让我这么做
…which prevented me doing so.
这是我 仅仅是我个人的责任
It is I, myself, who bear all responsibility…
为此我的良知一直在责备我
…for my conscience which troubles and doubts me.
庭上的先生们
Gentlemen of the court…
我只要求一点
…I ask for one thing and one thing only.
那就是公平
Justice.
稍后将要求王后陛下回应
In a moment, the court will call upon the queen's majesty…
陛下的陈述
…to reply to the king's statement.
但我得先告诉大家
But first, I must tell the court…
王后陛下咨询了她的顾问
…that the queen has sought, through her advisers…
她怀疑本庭处理此案的权力
…to question the competence of this court to try her case.
而且她怀疑法官的公正性
Further, she questions the impartiality of her judges.
最后 她要求将案件
Finally, she contends that this matter is in the hands…
交予更高的权威 也就是教皇之手
…of a higher authority, namely the pope…
这样就只能在罗马审理
…and therefore can only be tried in Rome.
现在 关于第一点置疑
Now, as for the first matter.
坎贝吉奥主教和我
Cardinal Campeggio and I can confirm…
都是由教皇亲自授权
…that we have the necessary authorization from His Holiness…
而在这里审理此案的
…to try this matter here.
进一步来说 我们将拒绝任何形式的不公正
Further, we reject any notion of prejudice on our part…
会继续审理此案 这是我们的职责
…and will continue to try the case here as we have been appointed.
现在请凯瑟林王后陛下 就此事发表看法
So I call upon Her Majesty, Queen Catherine, to address the court.
我的王上
My lord.
先生
Sir.
我乞求你
I beseech you…
看在我们之间曾经的感情份上
…for all the love that has been between us…
让我享有公平的权力
…let me have justice and right.
请给予我同情和怜悯 因为我只是个可怜的妇人 一个陌生人
Give me some pity and compassion, for I am a poor woman and a stranger…
生在您的疆域之外
…born out of your dominion.
我在这里没有朋友 也没有顾问
I have no friend here and little counsel.
我求助您 是因为您是正义的象征
I flee to you, as head of justice in this realm.
我请求上帝 以及全世界来为我作证
I call God and all the world to witness…
我是您谦卑恭顺的合法妻子
…that I have been to you a true, humble and obedient wife…
服从您的意愿 满足您的要求
…ever comfortable to your will and pleasure.
为了您 我爱您所爱的人
I have loved all those whom you have loved, for your sake.
无论我是否喜欢
Whether or not I had cause…
无论是敌是友
…whether they be my friends or enemies.
我们有过许多孩子
By me, you have had many children…
虽然都蒙上帝的召唤离开了人世
…although it has pleased God to call them from this world.
当你第一次占有我的时候
But when you had me at first…
上帝替我作证
…I take God as my judge…
我是处女 并没有被任何男人碰过
…I was a true maid without touch of man.
此话是真是假
And whether or not it be true…
你心知肚明
…I put it to your conscience.
- 现在她又要做什么 - 羞辱
- Now, what is she doing? - Shame.
英格兰王后 凯瑟林 回到庭上
Catherine, queen of England, come back into the court.
回到庭上
Come back into the court.
陛下也许该回去 在叫您呢
Perhaps Your Majesty should turn back. You are being called.
这个法庭对我毫无意义 我不会在这里待下去
This court has no meaning for me. Therefore, I will not stay here.
英格兰王后 凯瑟林
Catherine, queen of England…
回到庭上
…come back into the court.
她无视教会法
She spits in the face of papal law.
蔑视这个法庭
She holds this court in contempt.
陛下
Your majesty.